Today's דף daf is י"ח. yud-ches.
We start at the bottom of י"ז עמוד ב'. yud-zayin amud bet.
Okay.
אמר רב הונא, Amar Rav Huna, three lines from the bottom beginning
of the line, I mean רב הונא. Rav Huna. אמר Amar was
the last word of the previous line. Okay. אמר רב הונא בר
קטינא, Amar Rav Huna bar Kattina, so we're still, we're now getting
into the real details about the act of שחיטה shechita itself. So
רב הונא בר קטינא Rav Huna bar Kattina says אמר רבי שמעון
בן לקיש, Amar Rabbi Shimon ben Lakish, שלש פגימות הן, shalosh pegimot
hen, there are three types of nicks that you know are related
to one another in the terms of what is, what defines a
nick and where the nick is a problem. So what are those?
פגימת עצם בפסח, pegimat etzem bapesach, a nick in a bone on
פסח. Pesach. It says כל עצם לא תשברו בו, kol etzem lo
tishberu vo, don't break any bone. So surprisingly you might have thought
breaking a bone was literally snapping it in two, but no, actually
if you just nick a bone that is considered to be breaking
a bone. So that's one.
פגימת אוזן בבכור, pegimat ozen babechor, a nick in the ear of
a בכור, bechor, which is to make it a מום mum and
allows you to שחט shecht it and eat it outside of the
בית המקדש. Beit Hamikdash.
The reason it mentions an ear is because the ear, there's a
list of מומים mumim in a בכור bechor and the ear was
mentioned first. Also,
what?
צירם עין, tzeram ayin, right? I don't know.
What do you mean?
צירם עין, tzeram ayin, right? That was the case in the בית
המקדש.
Beit Hamikdash. Yeah, the eye. This is the ear. I know, I
know. Okay, anyway. So okay. So you have the ear of the
בכור bechor
and that a nick is considered a מום. mum. ופגימת מום בקדשים,
upegimat mum bekodashim, I'm sorry, and the a nick which creates a
blemish in קדשים. kodashim. So רש"י Rashi says well why should you
mention קדשים kodashim different from בכור? bechor? בכור bechor is a type
of a sacrifice. So he says two things. First of all בכורות
bechorot are only males, so there are certain blemishes that occur in
females and not in males, particularly you know in the you know
in the genital area. Number one. And
number two, that what constitutes a מום mum by a בכור, bechor,
you know there's a lot of what would constitute a מום mum
to allow it to be because when a בכור bechor has a
מום mum you slaughter it out of the בית המקדש. Beit Hamikdash.
It's not like קדשים kodashim where you transfer the קדושה kedusha and
you bring another קרבן. korban. So therefore you know what constitutes a
מום mum by בכור bechor in some ways could be a higher
threshold than what constitutes a מום mum by קדשים. kodashim. So רש"י
Rashi wants to mention them separately. Let me just read רש"י Rashi
on that.
Yeah קדשים kodashim
everywhere, בכור bechor is everywhere? Yeah.
One minute.
One minute I might have misstated this, hold on. Oh
yes, hold on. Yes, no audio, the audio should be on, hold
on.
Okay, there we go.
Okay, audio's on I hope. Okay.
All right, that was good that he was glitching me.
Okay, back to this. So okay, so yeah I actually misstated that,
so let me state that again. Okay, so there are three types
of מום, mum, let's do it again. אמר רב הונא בר קטינא
אמר רבי שמעון בן לקיש שלש פגימות הן. Amar Rav Huna bar
Kattina amar Rabbi Shimon ben Lakish shalosh pegimot hen. There are three
types of nicks. פגימת עצם בפסח, pegimat etzem bapesach, a nick in
a bone on פסח Pesach is the prohibition of כל עצם לא
תשברו בו, kol etzem lo tishberu vo, although it's not fully broken.
פגימת אוזן בבכור, pegimat ozen babechor, a nick in the ear of
a בכור bechor which is considered a מום. mum. And פגימת פגימת
where am I? ופגימת מום mum, בקדשים, a nick which creates a
blemish in קדשים kodashim which means that you can't bring it and
you have to transfer the קדושה. kedusha. רש"י Rashi says the reason
it says קדשים kodashim separately is number one because you have females,
so I know I'm repeating myself but anyway, you have a female,
and number two actually I had misstated this before, רש"י Rashi says
yeah it was רש"י Rashi says more what I was saying but
more as a הוה אמינא. hava amina. Meaning רש"י Rashi says I
might have thought that something might constitute a blemish for קדשים kodashim
and not allow it to be brought but maybe not be considered
a big enough blemish to allow it to be slaughtered outside of
the outside of the
מזבח mizbeach outside of the בית המקדש. Beit Hamikdash.
Okay, because it's a different stage, meaning one thing is it has
to be perfect to be a קרבן. korban. But by a בכור
bechor once it can't be a קרבן korban you can eat it
outside the בית המקדש. Beit Hamikdash. It's not like you have to
transfer the קדושה. kedusha. So I might think that to be at
a level where I can even eat it outside the בית המקדש,
Beit Hamikdash, you know that's maybe you require even a greater blemish.
You don't in the end, but I might have thought that, so
it mentioned בכור bechor separate from קדשים. kodashim.
So there's no middle there.
There's no middle, and that's exactly why it's saying both, right? Not
it was what I was saying but to exclude what I was
saying. Okay fine.
And that is just a nick also?
A nick, okay, in the right place though, I mean you know
some of this is also where did it occur, which we're not
getting into. ורב חסדא אמר אף פגימת סכין. VeRav Chisda amar af
pegimat sakkin. And the other says obviously the reason we're quoting this
is even a nick in a knife. ואידך, Ve'idach, so why was
that not said by the first opinion, the nick in the
knife? בחולין לא קא מיירי, bechullin lo ka mairi, we're not talking
about non-קדשים. kodashim. You're right nick in a knife is a thing.
Now obviously these are all nicks but okay why mention them together?
So they're mentioning together because the point is not just there're places
where nicks are a problem but the point is, is that they
are what do you call it? Is that they are the same
definition of a nick. And what is that definition? So now we're
going to say וכולם פגימתן כדי פגימת המזבח. Vechulam pegimatan kedei pegimat
hamizbe'ach. They all of their nicks is the same nick, it's like
you're always comparing to something else, is the same nick of what
constitutes a nick in the מזבח, mizbe'ach, in the altar, right? It
says אבנים שלמות תבנה את מזבח השם אלקיך, Avanim shelemot tivneh et
mizbach Hashem Elokecha, you know, לא תניף עליהם ברזל, lo tanif aleihem
barzel, so it has to be a whole stone, it cannot have
some type of instrument on them. So, and therefore if they are
nicked, they are not considered to be whole and it's a problem.
So it's the same definition of a nick there. Okay, that's very
lovely. What's the definition of a nick there?
So let's take a look. וכמה פגימת המזבח, vechama pegimat hamizbe'ach, what's
a nick there? כדי שתחגור בה ציפורן, kedei shetachgor bah tziporen,
which is exactly what we have been talking about now with our
knives, you know, so that if you run your finger by it
it gets caught. So if it's enough of a nick that your
finger gets caught, that is considered to be a nick in the
altar and you cannot bring קרבנות korbanot when the altar has a
nick in it, and similarly that would be considered a nick in
a bone to be a problem in the prohibition of breaking bones
on פסח, Pesach, or what would be a nick possibly for a
מום, for a blemish. Okay, so מיתיבי, meitivei, the גמרא Gemara says
I'll ask you on this. כמה פגימת המזבח? Kama pegimat hamizbe'ach? We
have a ברייתא braita that says what is considered to be a
nick in the altar? רבי שמעון בן יוחאי אומר טפח. Rabbi Shimon
ben Yochai omer tefach. It has to be an entire טפח, tefach,
which is, you know, let's face it, makes a little sense to
think that the altar has to be so smooth that you can't
run your fingernail on it and get it caught is a pretty
impossible standard. Without tools. Well, yeah, and that's the question תוספות Tosafot
asks, which we'll talk to in a minute. ולעזר בן יעקב אומר
כזית. Velazar ben Yaakov omer kezayit. Okay, it doesn't have to be
a whole טפח, tefach, but it still has to be the size
of an olive, it has to be a serious, you know, nick.
הגמרא haGemara says לא קשיא, lo kashya, it's not difficult. הא בסידא
הא באבנא. Ha besida ha be'avna. Difference between the plaster and the
stones. The plaster actually has to be, you know, the plaster, the
תורה Torah never says אבנים שלמות. avanim shelemot. So when you're dealing
with the plaster to be considered that the מזבח mizbe'ach is not
complete, it's only if it's missing a significant amount, an olive's worth
is indented or a, you know, or a טפח. tefach. But the
stones where the תורה Torah says אבנים שלמות, avanim shelemot, there even
the slightest nick makes a difference. Now תוספות Tosafot asks the obvious
question here: how the heck are you supposed to get it so
smooth if you're also not supposed to use any tools? And if
you take a look
at the first line of תוספות, Tosafot, וכמה פגימת המזבח כדי שתחגור
בה ציפורן. Vechama pegimat hamizbe'ach kedei shetachgor bah tziporen.
ואם תאמר והיך בנו המזבח? Ve'im tomar veheich banu hamizbe'ach? How could
they build it? ואנה ימצאו אבנים בלא פגימה? Ve'anna yimtze'u avanim belo
pegima? Where will you find stones that don't have any nicks in
them? ואם יחליקו בברזל איכא איסורא דלא תניף עליהם ברזל. Ve'im yachaliku
bevarzel ika issura delo tanif aleihem barzel. And if you, like, you
know, smooth it with iron,
you have a biblical prohibition. And of course the answer that everybody
loves is the גמרא Gemara speaks about this magical worm or something,
and that's not true, דליכא למימר נמי על ידי שמיר, Delika lemeimar
nami al yedei shamir, that we'll use this worm to smooth it.
דעל כרחך חייבי שמיר נמי לא יוכלו לחלקו שלא תחגור בהן ציפורן.
De'al korchacha chayvei shamir nami lo yuchlu lechaleko shelo tachgor bahen tziporen.
He then tries to prove that the שמיר shamir cannot get it
to be so smooth that it won't have a nick by the
what?
It's not that magical.
Right. By the what do you call it? By the fingernail. Now
if you remember when we learned in זבחים Zevachim how they built
the מזבח, mizbe'ach, it actually seems much more that they built it
as Michael said, basically you're pouring cement into a mold and they
didn't really build stone. And then if you have the poured cement
into a mold, you know, which is a mixture of gravel and
whatever else you use to make cement, I don't even know, but
anyway, you know, so it has stones, it is a stone altar,
but it's got all these other tiny little stones and therefore it's
able to be very smooth, it's in a mold. And that might
also help because the גמרא Gemara says here when you're dealing with
plaster, it's not a problem. Right now what plaster was the גמרא
Gemara talking about? It might have been referring to plaster that it
imagined like you build it like a brick wall, plaster between the
bricks. But what if your entire thing is made out of cement?
Does it go by the שיעור shiur of stones or does it
go by if it's enough stone to satisfy the תורה's Torah requirement
of a stone altar, but does it go by, you know, does
it go by the requirements here of stone or of plaster in
terms of the nick? Anyway, that's probably the best answer. תוספות Tosafot
comes around to that but he seems to do a twist on
it. If you look at the end of תוספות, Tosafot, he says
ויש לומר. Veyesh lomar. It's right above where it says in parentheses
זבחים נד. Zevachim nun-dalet. ויש לומר, Veyesh lomar, you could say דפרק
איזהו מקומן, deperek eizehu mekomon, I'm talking about the גמרא Gemara we
just referred to. משמע שבנו אותם באבנים קטנות חלקות שלא היה בהם
שום פגימה כגון חלוקי אבנים של נחל. Mashma shebanu otam be'avanim ketanot
chalakot shelo hayah bahem shum pegima kegon chalukei avanim shel nachal.
So he goes to the plaster explanation, but what he says is
the stone, he focuses on the individual stones in the plaster. Use
very smooth stones, pebbles from like a riverbed, right, that are very,
very smooth, they're smoothed by the water and they're held together by
all of the cement and the plaster whatever. So the individual stones
are perfectly smooth. So he goes to the plaster explanation but rather
than looking
at sort of the plaster as the say well there're no there's
no real stone here to talk about he says no you still
look at the individual stones and those are smooth. But in the
end if it's most of it or a lot of it is
really the plaster holding the stones together then effectively that plaster would
only be a problem if it were a טפח tefach or a
כזית. kezayit. So that's a realistic answer otherwise you know this seems
to be like an impossible standard. Okay so now the גמרא Gemara
continues. אמר רב הונא Amar Rav Huna so Rav Huna says האי
טבחא דלא סר סכינא קמי חכם hai tavcha dlo sar sakina kamei
chacham
if you have a butcher that does not show his knife to
the sage remember showing of the knife to the sage משמתינן ליה
meshamtinan lei
so you put him in חרם cherem for lacking either because he's
maybe trying to be deceitful and get by doing שחיטה shechita without
meeting the standards of the knife or at minimally because he's not
showing proper respect. Okay and if you look at רשי Rashi משמתינן
ליה meshamtinan lei משום mishum Rashi the first end of the first
wall the last wide line משום אפקירותא mishum afkirootah because of אפיקורס
apikoros actually now apikoros we normally translate as heresy but the גמרא
Gemara in סנהדרין Sanhedrin in the says that the word apikoros really
means somebody who is disrespectful of authority and of rabbinic authority. Okay
משהחציף פניו mishechechtzif panav that he's acting in a חוצפה chutzpah way
not to show proper respect. I know Rivka's very happy don't worry
Rivka it gets it gets better so let's keep on going.
Okay and is it כשרות kashrut wait
we're going to see we're going to see that in a second
we're going to see it. Okay you put him in חרם. cherem.
ורבא אמר VeRava amar
Rava says מעבירין ליה maavirin lei
you take him out of his post you basically prevent him from
being a butcher you do not let him to continue in his
job ומכרזינן אבשריה דטרפה umachrizinan abisreih detreifah and you announce that all
of his meat should be considered טרפה treifah because he refused to
show his knife to the sage. Now that's pretty severe. So the
גמרא Gemara tries to reconcile it and tone it down a bit.
ולא פליגי Velo peligi it doesn't really debate they don't really debate
כאן שנמצא סכינו יפה כאן שלא נמצא סכינו יפה. kan shenimtza sakino
yafeh kan shelo nimtza sakino yafeh. The question is is what actually
was the story with his knife? Okay he didn't show it to
the חכם. chacham. That was a problem he didn't do the right
procedure he didn't show the right respect. But what really was the
story you went and you checked his knife. If in the end
his knife was okay he just lacked a proper deference and respect
then you put him in חרם cherem which eventually presumably he can
get out of you know he does תשובה teshuvah gets out of
it or whatever and that's not a permanent type of a thing
but it's a way of showing you know that you don't accept
the disrespect. If however his knife wasn't good so then not only
was it a it was טרפה treifah it wasn't only an error
but it was actually a deception right he knew perhaps that he
was not doing quality and he was trying to avoid being found
out. That's real problem so there you basically have to announce you
know treat all of his meat as טרפה treifah and kick him
out. So that makes a certain amount of sense. The point problem
is Rivka doesn't like it wait because we're not even going to
end there so let's take a look. No let's take a look
at let's read a little bit more about this. רבינא אמר Ravina
amar Ravina says no היכא דלא נמצא סכינו יפה heicha delo nimtza
sakino yafeh if his knife actually is not
is not good had a nick in it then we wouldn't stop
by just saying that his meat was טרפה. treifah. We would go
even further ממרמסינן ליה בפרתא memarmesinan lei beparta you would literally drag
his meat in dung דאפילו לעובדי כוכבים נמי לא מזדבן deafilu leovdei
kochavim nami lo mizdaben to prevent him even selling it to a
non-Jew. If it were just a טרפה treifah obviously you could sell
it
to a non-Jew but if this guy is not a he's he's
not been careful in his שחיטה shechita and b I think the
important the other additional point here is b he's trying to get
away with it he knows it and he's trying to be deceitful
so then you have to a you know you have to have
not just the obvious הלכה halacha consequence which is announce that it's
טרפה treifah but you have to actually take measures to prevent this
type of thing from happening again and punish and fine him and
therefore not even allow him to sell it to non-Jews. So what
according to רבינא Ravina on the one hand not only do we
have a very heavy fine levied against the person that was actually
not being careful and deceitful but he would then say he that
the second position of who was it רבא Rava that says that
you kick him out of his post was talking that his knife
actually was good right so this so what רבינא Ravina is actually
saying is is it Ravina am I saying it right hold on
yeah רבינא Ravina Ravina is actually saying is he believes in a
very heavy fine. So you know if the guy was actually doing
a good שחיטה shechita but just not showing it to the רב
Rav then well then we have a punishment which is very serious
punishment which is we basically you know kick him out of his
post and announce that his meat is טרפה treifah even though it
isn't even though it isn't yeah and put him in חרם cherem
presumably yeah and put him in second. If actually he really was
what you know did with that knife and was being deceitful then
we don't even let him sell it to non-Jews. So according to
רבינא Ravina it's very very heavy the consequences even in the case
I mean personally to me in the case where the guy actually
was being deceitful and was שוחט shechting and was using a bad
knife it doesn't bother me so much why should. just with the
natural consequences, why shouldn't there be an actual serious penalty and fine
and punishment? But for the case of the person that's just not
doing the proper respect with the rabbi and his שחיטה shechita actually
is good, you know, it seems obviously quite severe to be deposing
him from his post. And there's going to be a story exactly
about this tension. Rivka, what do you want to say?
Well, this shows why
Conservative, etc., people say don't eat from a השגחה. Hashgacha. Hebrew National
may be totally kosher, but we can't use it because it's not
they're not respectful of the OU or whatever it is. And this
has tremendous implications where in a community like Silver Spring where they
have to they're limited to use only one השגחה Hashgacha even though
another השגחה Hashgacha is completely fine. But that's what the community rabbis
say, you can only use this one.
Right, right.
I'm not sure. So I think you are correct that this plays
out much more at the local communal השגחה, hashgacha, you know, הכשר
hechsher level. I don't know you talk about a whole series of
problems with השגחות, hashgachas, with you
know Hebrew National and so on. But
I'm not sure it's the same dynamics. But certainly I think at
the local communal level, you know, you're right that this does play
out. You have a lot of times where you have a local
השגחה, Hashgacha, community השגחה, Hashgacha, and that, you know, other restaurants or
whatever, you know, that are totally kosher can't be approved because they
have a different השגחה Hashgacha and
there's a lot of issues. But this has nothing to do with
כשרות kashrut at all. It has to do with rabbinic control and
financial control.
Well, okay. In the גמרא, Gemara, it was not financial. What it
is nowadays, right. And again, I'm not sure. Certainly the rabbis were
concerned about ensuring rabbinic respect, you know, and being very serious. Look,
the whole discussion about נידוי niduy is a whole, you know, many
many of the examples in the גמרא Gemara about when you put
somebody in נידוי niduy is because of because of disrespect of the
rabbis. Now the question is, was this a personal thing that they
felt, you know, they needed personally, they were concerned about their own
personal respect, or was this a concern about, you know, about creating
the right type of culture and attitude that people actually would observe
הלכה Halacha and listen to rabbinic authorities? So, you know, I mean
I'm not so sure you are correct that that was the concern,
but I'm not so sure that it was a personal issue rather
than a desire for ultimately, you know, having people... I mean I
don't understand why you don't understand that. Because is it כשרות kashrut
because of the... Yes! In this case. But if you have a
culture, but if you have a culture where the rabbis are not
respected and people say yeah what do the rabbis know and I'm
good enough to check my own knife and dot dot dot dot
dot, is that in the end a healthy type of a culture
in terms of for observance and for... so I don't know. You're
right it's about respect,
but alright, so there's a question about where you draw the lines.
Yeah, but on the other hand you've got when רב Rav סולובייצ'יק
Soloveitchik was practically run out of Boston when he was trying to
enforce some standards and he was justified because the kosher butchers were
cutting corners left and right and
firing employees who wouldn't be dishonest. That's different.
Yeah, but the point is if you don't have a culture about
being about rabbinic authority and about submitting to rabbinic authority, then when
rabbis try to stand up for things that matter, whether they're ethical
issues or whether they're כשרות kashrut issues,
right, then they have no power.
I don't think for example, I don't think there would have been
all these issues about rabbinic respect if they had a police force
behind them. You know? I mean, but if you don't have a
police force behind you, so you need a certain culture of adherence.
That's the way I understand it. I'm not saying that it's a
totally neutral thing, but I don't think it's... I think they had
sort of, you know, the community's religious interests in mind. It wasn't
a personal issue.
But this is what I was trying to understand, because as far
as I understood based on what you mentioned earlier is that it's
sort of like a one-time thing showing the rabbi, right? When you
move into the community. So what would happen, this guy's there for
20 years, he showed it to the rabbi year
one, then he decided, you know what, okay, I kind of duped
the rabbis, and then for the next 19 years he's
שוחט shechting with the same...
is it the same thing? He showed it to the rabbi.
I think rabbis
can set up, whoever the חכם chacham is can set up like
requirements, like I want to see it once a year, you know,
whatever the case might be. It doesn't have to be limited to
just once. The point is it doesn't have to be every time.
No, but is the point also that even after he showed it,
would the same punishment happen?
That I don't know. It depends I guess what the... I suppose
it depends what system the rabbi's setting up.
טוב. Tov. Okay. Alright, so let's continue. I understand the problem. I
just think that we should not make them out to be just,
you know, purely self-serving in the process. I'm not saying it's not
problematic, but I don't think it's completely self-serving. Okay, so let's go
on. So the גמרא Gemara says like this:
Okay so ההוא טבחא, hahu tibcha, now we're gonna have a story.
There was a butcher דלא אחזי סכינא קמיה דרבה בר בר חנה.
d'lo achzei sakina kamei d'Rabba Bar Bar Chana. He didn't show his
knife to Rabba Bar Bar Chana. שמתיה, shamtei, so he, Rabba Bar
Bar Chana, followed the more severe position of Rav. שמתיה, shamtei, he
put him in חרם, cherem, ועבריה, v'avrei, and he took him out
of his
post, ואכריז אבשרא דטרפה היא, v'achriz a'bisra d'treifa hi, and he announced
that the meat was טרפה. treif. So איקלעו מר זוטרא ורב אשי
לגביה, iklu Mar Zutra v'Rav Ashi lgabei, so Mar Zutra and Rav
Ashi came to this person, to Rabba Bar Bar
Chana. אמר להו, amar lehu, so he said to them, ליעיינו רבנן
במילתיה, le'ayeinu rabanan b'miltei, go go check into this case. I had
this case but it's bothering me. Like he did what he thought
he had to do,
but then it was weighing on his conscience. So he said to
these visiting rabbis, would you mind go look into this
case דתלו ביה טפלי, d'talu bei taflei, because he has a lot
of kids that are dependent on him. So he felt a little
bad for the butcher. I kicked him out of his post but
I know that he's supporting a family, his kids are starving, so
could you like maybe investigate this case a little bit see see
if we can do something? So בדק רב אשי לסכיניה, badak Rav
Ashi l'sakiniei, so Rav Ashi checked the knife. Seems like this was
the first time that anybody bothered to check the knife. This was
the reaction as soon as the guy didn't show his knife, so
he checked the knife ונמצאת יפה, v'nimtzas yafa, the knife actually was
good. ואכשריה, v'achshrei, he said okay, it's kosher, your meat is kosher,
you can go back into business. So אמר ליה מר זוטרא לרב
אשי, amar lei Mar Zutra l'Rav Ashi, so Mar Zutra said to
Rav Ashi, ולא ליחוש למר לסבא, v'lo leichush Mar l'Saba, are you
not concerned about the elder? Meaning, obviously when Rabba Bar Bar Chana
deposed him, he was following the position that regardless of the quality
of the knife, this guy should be kicked out of his post.
So how are you, how are you putting... what?
It means he didn't check the knife.
But it means he didn't feel the knife was relevant. He feels
if you're not showing me your knife, I'm kicking you out of
your post.
But if you find the knife has a nick, then you do
the step more, but he only did the more...
that I don't know, maybe, but it doesn't matter, he felt minimally
what he did was he vet... that you always kick the guy
out of his post. So how are you taking the more lenient
position here? Aren't you concerned about what the elder did? אמר ליה,
amar lei, שליחותיה עבדינן. shlichutei avdinan. Yes, but I'm doing his, his,
what do you call it, his... what? His orders, right, meaning he
asked me to try to find a way out. So okay, I'm
finding a way out. I found that the knife was okay, there's
a different position to rely on, that if the knife is okay
then maybe you put him in חרם cherem or whatever but at
least you let him keep on in his business. So that's what
I'm doing. He asked me to help him and I'm helping him.
Doesn't חרם cherem mean he can't have any הנאה hana'ah from the
guy?
Yeah, well there's no, I used the phrase חרם cherem a little
loosely. There's also like a weaker form which is נידוי, niduy, which
is more what you use when people are disrespectful of rabbinic authority,
which is a type of a, it has more implications for less
for how we interact with the guy and more for the guy
himself, what type of practices he has to adopt.
And avoid him socially because he'll buy his meat...
Yeah and also, yeah, it's more about, right, about himself, he has
to be נוהג noheig certain מנהגים minhagim like that are similar to
אבילות, aveilus, okay, but it's less about the community cutting him off.
You're right, חרם cherem is, I was being imprecise, it's more of
נידוי, niduy, and also there, if the guy does תשובה teshuva or
whatever, then we remove it. We don't know if he did תשובה
teshuva here. I know, but I'm just saying the נידוי niduy is
not a permanent state. Yeah, Dov?
Well, it's interesting that the guy shows his knife to Rav Ashi
but not to Rabba Bar Bar Chana.
It's a question whether Rabba Bar Bar Chana bothered to ask for
the knife. That's the way I read it. He refused to show
the knife, Rabba Bar Bar Chana says fine, you're in, here's what
we do to people who don't show me their knife. Right, why
should I bother even looking at your knife?
But then when he says Rav Ashi, let me see the knife,
then he shows him. Right. I wonder if it was the first,
there's some kind of a, some kind of a personal clash.
That could be.
I think that goes back to the point of what I was
thinking about before, is that it's so hard to draw any conclusions
from this story because there are so many factors
that you don't even know where to start, between the personal and
so on.
Right, is it the rabbis and their personality, what would you do
if the guy did not have kids dependent on
him, and what if an alternate כשרות kashrut agency has an actually
different type of opinion with the first one and there's all kinds
of history that you can read whatever you want or you can
read, you can reject
any...
Exactly, and I think the point that Charlie made before
is the flip side of this. We could be offended by how
heavy-handed the rabbis are, but very often the meat industry, at least
today, I don't know in the, was very very powerful and the
rabbis
have very little influence and power.
So there are some important dynamics here and it's not always the
rabbis that are trying to be
overly use their authority in improper ways.
Yeah, and most of the כשרות kashrut scandals you read about in
the newspaper involve non-kosher meat often snuck in right under the nose
of a משגיח. mashgiach.
If people
really want to cheat it's hard to catch them.
Right, right, exactly. Anyway, definitely food for thought. Excuse. Okay, so let's
finish up this discussion. Hopefully כשר kosher food for thought. Exactly.
Okay. אמר רבה בר רב הונא Amar Raba bar Rav Huna שית
שלוחות sheis sheluchos we're going to finally go back to our משנה
mishna and the discussion about using a tooth and a fingernail for
שחיטה. shechitah. So if you have a detached tooth,
וציפורן תלושה, v'tziporen tlushah, a detached fingernail, מותר לשחוט בה, mutar lishchot
bah, you can shecht with it. Why not? You can use a
rock, you can use a reed, so you can use these things
as well. לכתחילה, lechatchila, even at the outset. תנן, tnan, our משנה
mishna says, חוץ ממגל קציר והמגירה, chutz mimagal katzir v'hamigerah, you cannot
use a scythe and a saw, והשיניים והציפורן, v'hashinayim v'hatziporen, teeth and
a fingernail, מפני שהן חונקין, mipnei shehein chonkin, they cause, you know,
they're... so the first cases are serrated, but then it says that
all these things are serrated and cause the animal to choke rather
than to just cut with the sharpness of the knife. So the
גמרא Gemara says, שן אשן לא קשיא, shein ashein lo kashya, the
case about the tooth is not difficult. הא בחדא הא בתרתי. ha
b'chada ha b'tartei. It said שיניים, shinayim, teeth. So if you use
two teeth, obviously if they're still attached to the jaw, so obviously
if you're using two teeth they're bumpy and there's a gap between
them and that's like a serration. Even if the teeth themselves have
been sort of sharpened and smoothed. ציפורן אציפורן לא קשיא, tziporen atziporen
lo kashya, nail on a nail is not a problem. הא בתלושה
הא במחוברת, ha bitlusha ha bimchuberet, like Michael said, is it detached
or attached? If it's detached it's fine. If it's attached, that's then
according to רבי Rebbi that says it cannot be attached to the
ground, attached to a person or attached to an animal is a
similar problem as attached to the ground, which we haven't said yet
but we're saying now, and therefore it would be no good. Okay,
so with that we end the discussion, well, not that discussion, about
the knives. We have one final mini little discussion and then we
start turning to the question about where the שחיטה shechitah is done.
So let's look at this next משנה, mishna, one final little discussion
about the knives.
השוחט במגל קציר בדרך הליכתה, hashocheit bimagal katzir b'derech halichatah, so you
actually are using this harvest scythe which is something that has serrations,
but you do it in the normal way of cutting, the normal
motion of movement. בית שמאי פוסלין ובית הלל מכשירין. Beis Shammai poslin
u'Beis Hillel machshirin. Beis Shammai says it's no good and Beis Hillel
says it's good. Now this is quite bizarre because our previous... I
will tell you, because our previous משנה mishna said that a harvest
scythe is not good, but this is a type of a case
where the way רשי Rashi describes it, it's a specific... I mean
it's not clear from this משנה mishna that this is true and
this really actually does seem to contradict the previous משנה, mishna, but
anyway where the serrations are at such a small angle that
if you're moving in line with the serrations rather than against the
serrations, it basically the entire surface is smooth. Like if you can
imagine serrations that like lie on top of each other sort of
like this. So if you're going in line with the serrations, right,
it's a totally smooth surface. If you're going in the opposite direction...
like I said just think about
the
rent-a-cars when you return it, right? If you go one way it's
totally smooth, you go the other way your tires get shredded. Now
that's also I think because the thingies move. But anyway, but if
they're laid down in the direction of the movement, right, it could
be a totally smooth surface going this way and it could be
a total cutting surface going the other way. So that's at least
the... רשי Rashi explains that this is, although before we said that
even sort of you know one-way bumps are a problem לכתחילה lechatchila
and you can't do it unless it's at the tip of the
knife and so on, רשי Rashi said that this is a very
specific type of a serration which is totally smooth in one direction.
That's the way רשי Rashi reads it. Okay, ואם החליקו שיניה, v'im
hechliku shineha,
and if you actually
smoothed the teeth, הרי היא כסכין, harei hi k'sakin, then everybody would
agree that it's like a knife, presumably even בית שמאי. Beis Shammai.
So if you smooth the teeth, I assume this means even more,
or maybe it means in the opposite direction you blunted the teeth,
I really have to tell you I'm not getting the full sense
of this. But somehow if you did it in a way in
which obviously there would be no serrations, even בית שמאי Beis Shammai
would agree. So אמר רבי חייא בר אבא אמר רבי יוחנן, Amar
Rabbi Chiya bar Abba amar Rabbi Yochanan, אף כשמכשירין בית הלל, af
keshemachshirin Beis Hillel, לא הכשירו אלא לטהרה מידי נבלה. lo hechshiru ela
l'taharah midei neveilah. That even when Beis Hillel says it's okay, they
didn't really say that the meat was kosher. They just said that
it's not going to be treated as a נבלה. neveilah. But we're
still going to be treated... obviously we're because they were concerned, the
way רשי Rashi explains it, it's גזירה. gezeirah. We're concerned if we
allow you to do it in one way, you'll come to do
it the other way. And the other way is where you hit
all the serrations, where you do all the cutting.
So Beis Hillel
rabbinically forbade the meat. So when it says מכשירין, machshirin, it doesn't
mean really מכשירין, machshirin, it means it's not נבלה neveilah because they
realize the meat is kosher but they still do not allow you
to eat the meat. They just say it's not נבלה. neveilah. בית
שמאי Beis Shammai makes the גזירה gezeirah either he thinks that it
really is נבלה neveilah or they made the גזירה gezeirah even further
to treat the meat as total נבלה. neveilah. Okay.
So they still won't allow it... won't allow it for consumption. Beis
Shammai won't allow it for consumption
and treat it as נבלה. neveilah.
Meaning in terms of טומאה?
tumah? טומאה וטהרה. tumah v'taharah. Yes. Yeah, yeah, the נבלה neveilah issue
is only for טומאה וטהרה. tumah v'taharah. Okay, now he's picking... so
now where does he get that from? אבל באכילה אסור. aval b'achilah
assur. It's forbidden in eating. אמר רב אשי, Amar Rav Ashi, דיקא
נמי, dayka nami, that's inferred from the language of the משנה, mishna,
דקתני בית שמאי פוסלין ובית הלל מכשירין. diktani Beis Shammai poslin u'Beis
Hillel machshirin. Beis Shammai invalidates and Beis Hillel says... כשר, kasher, ולא
תני בית שמאי אוסרין ובית הלל מתירין. v'lo tani Beit Shammai osrin
u'Beit Hillel matirin. Now this is a fascinating little reflection, why do
you use the word כשר kasher and פסול, pasul, right, what's the
word פסול pasul by meat anyway? פסול. pasul. פסול pasul usually means
invalid to use for certain things. It should be, it should be
כשר kasher and not כשר, kasher, right, it should be אוסרין, osrin,
forbid it, and מתירין, matirin, permit it, not פוסל posel and כשר.
kasher. So therefore to say, rather than
say forbid and permit, to say פוסלין ומכשירין poslin u'machshirin suggests that
we're talking about something more ritual and not just eating meat. So
we're talking about its whether it creates a טומאה tumah problem and
not whether it is a, and not whether it is a כשרות
kashrus problem. Everybody agrees not you can't eat it for a כשרות
kashrus perspective. Okay, so that's what he says. ולא תני בית שמאי
אוסרין ובית הלל מתירין. v'lo tani Beit Shammai osrin u'Beit Hillel matirin.
So the גמרא Gemara says דאי הכי לישתני בית שמאי מטמאין ובית
הלל מטהרין. d'i hachi lishtani Beit Shammai mitamin u'Beit Hillel m'taharin. No,
but if it was really about טומאה וטהרה, tumah v'taharah, we have
more specific verbs for that. Say בית שמאי Beit Shammai says it's
טמא tamei and בית הלל Beit Hillel says it's טהור. tahor. אלא
פוסלין ומכשירין ואוסרין ומתירין חדא מילתא היא. ella poslin u'machshirin v'osrin u'matirin
chada milta hi. To say פסול pasul or כשר kasher and מותר
mutar and אסור asur is more or less the same, okay? Because
you say the שחיטה, shechita, the act of שחיטה, shechita, is פסול
pasul or כשר, kasher, which means the meat is אסור asur or
מותר. mutar. So yes, פסול pasul or כשר kasher refers not to
the meat, but to the act of שחיטה, shechita, and it really
and really this is not a debate about טומאה וטהרה, tumah v'taharah,
it's a debate fundamentally about whether the meat is kosher or not.
So here we have a case where בית הלל Beit Hillel does
allow one type of a knife that is serrated as long as
you're going in the non-serrated direction, which ties back to the earlier
discussion about different types of serrations.
Can you actually though eat it?
No, that's only according to רבי חייא בר אבא. Rabbi Chiya bar
Abba. The גמרא Gemara rejects רבי חייא. Rabbi Chiya.
Okay, so in the end בית הלל Beit Hillel says it's actually
כשר לכתחילה? kasher l'chatchila?
That's the way, that's the way the סתם stam against רבי חייא
בר אבא. Rabbi Chiya bar Abba. רבי חייא בר אבא Rabbi Chiya
bar Abba presumably was motivated to say otherwise because he didn't like
the idea based on the previous גמרא Gemara about ever using anything
with serrations. You know, so that was the obviously the emphasis of
the previous גמרא. Gemara. Yes.
I was wondering all this discussion with what kind of tools, could
they be economically in certain communities people certainly could not afford a
proper.
I don't know, that's an interesting question. I don't I can't answer
whether they could afford it or not, but I do know that
these were the most common tools you had around. If you're in
an agricultural community, you have a scythe around, you know? Although again,
I'm not exactly sure about the mechanics of using a scythe to
cut the neck, you would think you would want to use a
straight knife, I mean. But yes, I don't know.
Yes, there are hand, yeah,
that was the מגל יד, magal yad, that was mentioned before. This
is the מגל קציר. magal katzir. The מגל קציר magal katzir is
much larger. Yeah, huge. Yeah, I don't know, I don't know, I
don't know. It's a good question whether they were just doing this
as more of a intellectual exercise or whether it was really people
actually were doing it. Yeah, I don't know. Right. Now we get
to the actual act of שחיטה shechita itself, where in the neck
of the animal. Okay, so let's take a look. השוחט. hashocheit. Now,
I made actually, I xeroxed off from a book not about animals,
I know we have in this picture, but anyway, about humans, made
it a little more at home. But I thought maybe we could
relate to it a little bit more, if you take a look
there about the about the view here of the trachea. If you
take a look the trachea, which is what we're going to be
talking about, the קנה kanah is it's got rings around it, right?
I mean, if you feel in your throat, right, you feel bumps.
Is that are those the same bumps? I don't even know, I
think they are. Anyway, it has rings around it. What? Dr. Yehuda.
Okay, anyway, so if you take a look at it, right, near
the top here, and you know, this picture here on the on
the left, the full picture, the larynx, the one which is basically
the trachea, right? So if you see the larynx the trachea, well,
I don't know, I guess the larynx is the top, the trachea
starts underneath. Anyway, so if you take a look, you'll see that
this this huge cap on the top, right? And then under it
starts individual like little like rows of cartilage or bone or whatever.
So if you take a look where it says posterior view, you
see that those rings of rings, those hard rings don't go all
the way around. But the top, you know, thing is obviously, you
know, is completely around and it's this huge thing where also ultimately
the top of it is is the epiglottis, you know, and so
on and where the flap opens up. Now, where the שחיטה shechita
is כשר kasher from this big top unit, somewhere in this big
top unit to all the way to the to the lungs. Okay,
we're going to be talking about the שחיטה shechita if you're doing
the שחיטה shechita in this top ring. So let's take a look
at the משנה. mishna. Yeah, in that yeah, exactly, in that top
ring. So let's take a look at the משנה. mishna. It says
השוחט מתוך הטבעת, hashocheit mitoch hatabaat,
you're doing a שחיטה shechita in the middle of this ring. Now,
there's a big question how to read this, but רש"י Rashi reads
this to mean this top ring, okay? And the the issue for
רש"י Rashi is the following: we're going to deal with the פסול
psul called
הגרמה. hagrama. Remember there are five פסולים psulim by שחיטה, shechita, שהייה,
shehiya, דרסה, drasa, one is הגרמה. hagrama. What does הגרמה hagrama mean?
הגרמה hagrama means that during the act of שחיטה, shechita, the knife
goes outside of the שחיטה shechita area. Now, what that's going to
mean for רש"י Rashi is the following: you're שחט'ing shechting at the
very top edge of the trachea. right at the very limit of
where the מקום השחיטה makom hashechita is. You're doing that שחיטה. shechita.
Let's assume you שחט-ed shecht-ed and you did the majority. Majority here
means to the depth, obviously you're doing the you're cutting it. But
the depth is, if you imagine that this is a thing, the
way you define the majority of the סימן, siman, which is what
you need for it to be כשר, kosher, is that you cut
into half of the hollow. You know, you don't sort of measure
the half by the thickness of the of whatever the skin or
whatever around it, but you know, obviously this is a tube. So
you have to get into a little bit more than half of
the hollow of the tube. Is that clear what I mean? Right
you cut through more than half the hollow of the tube. Okay.
So you're you're cutting, now you could cut the whole thing through.
You're cutting, you cut half. Before you finish cutting the whole thing,
you're right at the top of the כשר kosher place to do
the שחיטה, shechita, you moved your knife up and you finished cutting
the remaining minority in the non-שחיטה shechita place. Now you might think
look, since I did the first part good and שחיטה shechita only
has to be רוב סימן, rov siman, it's okay. But this becomes
the question of רובו ככולו. rubo kechulo. When we say רוב rov
is enough, do we say fundamentally the only requirement is to cut
fifty-one percent? Or do we say no, in principle the requirement is
to cut one hundred percent, but if you cut fifty-one percent it's
like you cut the whole thing. The relevance is, what if you
introduce a you do cut the whole thing and the last half
of it was problematic? This could be because it was in the
wrong place or could be other things. Let's say you do a
שהייה shehiya or דרסה, drasa, you pause or you do pressure in
the last forty-nine percent. Does that invalidate or once you do fifty-one
percent it's fine? So the תנא קמא tanna kamma here is going
to assume that if you finish it, the last part also matters.
Okay, so you did the first half fifty-one percent good, then you
moved your knife up and it was in the wrong place in
the last part, that's going to be the problem here about הגרמה.
hagrama. Okay, that even though the שחיטה shechita was done, since it
ended in a non-כשר kosher place, it's not good. So let's read
the משנה: mishna: השוחט מתוך הטבעת, Hashocheit mitoch hataba'at, you're שחט-ing shecht-ing
within this top ring, ושייר בה מלא חוט על פני כולה, veshiyir
ba melo chut al pnei kula, and you are right at the
edge, there is a hairbreadth of a skin of width above where
you're שחט-ing shecht-ing till you get to the till you get to
the no-שחיטה shechita zone. Okay? So you're right at the very, very
top edge of where it's כשר. kosher.
שחיטתו כשרה, Shechitatu keshera, it is good. רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה אומר:
Rabbi Yose berabbi Yehuda omer: מלא חוט על פני רובה. melo chut
al pnei ruba. No, it's not על פני כולה, al pnei kula,
you don't need to have that you're in the safe zone for
all of it, you only need to be in the safe zone
for the majority of it. But if you end it with being
in the non-good zone, you're okay as long as the first half
of it or fifty-one percent was good. So here's this question about
do you have to do the entire if you do the entire
amount, do you have to end it in the good place or
not? Do we say that only we only focus on the רוב
rov or do we focus on the entire? And the פסול psul
here is called the פסול psul of הגרמה, hagrama, which is moving
the שחיטה shechita knife to a non-כשר kosher place of שחיטה. shechita.
רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose is clarifying?
No, he's disagreeing. He is saying I don't care what happens in
the last forty-nine percent. I only care what happens in the first
fifty-one percent. And if you end it with the knife not being
you have רוב rov was good, רוב rov of the סימן siman
was good, even if you end it in a non-acceptable place it's
still okay. Alright, so let's take a look at the גמרא. gemara.
רב ושמואל דאמרי תרוייהו, Rav u'Shmuel d'amri tarveihu, רב Rav and שמואל
Shmuel both say הלכה כרבי יוסי ברבי יהודה. halacha keRabbi Yose berabbi
Yehuda. We rule like רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה, Rabbi Yose berabbi Yehuda,
which is good, makes שחיטה shechita easier. You don't have to worry
about what happens after the first fifty-one percent. Now keep this in
mind, is this הלכה halacha going to remain the same when we
get to other פסולים? psulim? Like שהייה shehiya and דרסה, drasa, what
if you do those wrong in the last forty-nine percent, which you
didn't have to do, but you did it and you did it
incorrectly? Okay, but for now we're ruling like רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה
Rabbi Yose berabbi Yehuda that הגרמה hagrama in the last
מיעוט miyut is not a problem.
ואף רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה לא אמר אלא בטבעת הגדולה. Ve'af Rabbi
Yose berabbi Yehuda lo amar ela betaba'at hagedola. Now we're going to
add to it. He's only saying this by this big ring, which
is, you know, this part on the top, הואיל ומקפת את כל
הקנה, ho'il umakefet et kol hakaneh, because it completely circles the trachea,
as you see in the picture. אבל בשאר טבעות, Aval bish'ar taba'ot,
but by the other rings, לא. lo. They do not circle the
entire trachea and therefore no. No what? So there's רש״י, Rashi, in
a very uncharacteristic way, י׳ yod רש״י-s, Rashis, trying to figure out
what's going on here. The explanation that רש״י Rashi likes the best,
which is a little bizarre because it's totally unrelated to the previous
point, is that if you שחט shecht in this ring place lower
down, it's not considered like you're שחט-ing shecht-ing in the actual trachea.
Since this ring does not circle the entire trachea, therefore it's not
considered these other rings, they're not considered to be part of the
trachea itself. So if you're שחט-ing shecht-ing in this lower part of
the trachea underneath this big bone on the top or whatever it
is, you have to שחט shecht directly in the skin location, not
at the ring location.
Meaning you gotta get in between rings?
You gotta get in between the rings, which is pretty difficult. Okay.
Now the גמרא gemara is going to reject that להלכה, lehalacha, but
that's the way it's reading it. Now that has nothing to do
with
the... Maybe the better read and the read that תוספות Tosafot likes
is the following
is that hold on let me just double-check תוספות Tosafot
and רש״י Rashi actually suggests this read of תוספות Tosafot but he
rejects it.
Oh he says like this:
that when we say that it's enough to do the majority of
the ring, that's true, this is almost an obvious statement, that's true
if the ring goes all the way around, then if the ring
goes all the way around and you do the majority of the
ring, you're also doing you're getting into the you know the majority
of the hollow of the thing itself because the ring is completely
sort of equal on all sides, but if the ring only goes
partially around and you do the majority of the ring, so the
majority of the ring doesn't get you 51% in right because you
measure because the majority of the ring you're not measuring you know
you're not measuring the entire distance around because the ring itself doesn't
go the entire distance around, so doing the majority of the ring
doesn't suffice because it doesn't get you into the majority of the
trachea because the ring itself does not go all the way around
the trachea. Okay so then it's a relatively minor point which is
I mean not minor but it's like almost self-evident point that you
cannot measure you know how deep you went relative to the ring
if the ring itself does not go completely around. All right the
third possibility which I should mention that רש״י Rashi recognizes as a
very reasonable read of the משנה Mishna of the גמרא Gemara but
he very much resists is that the idea about הגרמה hagrama applies
not to I should mention it just so you should be aware
that the idea of הגרמה hagrama applies not just to the top
ring but it applies to any ring that if you're שוחט shechting
your knife goes into any one of the rings that you have
to finish within the ring and it can't leave the ring. So
whereas the way רש״י Rashi rejected that and he says no the
only problem is if you go too high you go beyond the
upper limit of the מקום השחיטה makom hashchita this other read would
say anywhere you're doing the שחיטה shchita if you're doing it in
a ring itself it has to stay within the ring until it
finishes. So right there's not a good explanation why. It would just
be like any other law of שחיטה shchita הלכה למשה מסיני Halacha
le-Moshe mi-Sinai or something.
So then what happens if you start in between and end in
between?
That he didn't say, but if you do start in the ring
you have to end in the ring. But רש״י Rashi rejects that
read of the גמרא Gemara but that is one way to read
the משנה Mishna to read the ongoing discussions in the גמרא Gemara
I'm just mentioning it because it actually makes some of the reading
of the גמרא Gemara easier but for other reasons רש״י Rashi rejects
it and it's also a bizarre way of understanding.
You don't like the word הגרמה? hagrama?
I'm trying to understand how that. Yeah I don't know I mean
הגרמה hagrama means going in the wrong place. It sort of means
like I think it's from the same word as גרמא grama to
to like to cause to to cause but it would mean here
like to I might be wrong to cause the knife to move
incorrectly but I'm not sure. I actually I should have looked it
up.
Applies to esophagus as well?
What? I thought it'd affect it. You do but we're focusing now
on the trachea. Okay how you would be talk later about the
esophagus here focusing on doing it at the trachea correctly. Yes.
Could even be like a spasm so even if you start off...
Yeah but it could be that's not your fault. Right. Look I
understand I'm just saying so רש״י's Rashi read both because it's more
logical to limit the problem to going too high you know and
not a general problem and also makes it much more reasonable in
terms of getting a kosher שחיטה. shchita. So let's take a look.
So the גמרא Gemara says ובשאר טבעות לא Ubishar taba'ot lo are
you telling me that in the other rings it's not the case?
Again we'll read this let's say for argument's
sake like תוספות. Tosafot. By other rings it's not enough to go
the
majority? והתניא Vhatanya didn't we teach רבי יוסף ברבי
יהודה אומר Rabbi Yosef be-Rabbi Yehuda omer השוחט בשאר טבעות Ashochet bishar
taba'ot if you שוחט shecht in the other rings אף על פי
שאין מקיפות את כל הקנה af al pi she'ein makifot et kol
hakane although they do not totally surround it הואיל ומקיפות רוב הקנה
ho'il umakifot rov hakane since they surround the majority of the trachea
שחיטתו כשרה shchitatu keshera it is valid. So the way רש״י Rashi
reads it is that the suggestion was that he would say you
can't do the שחיטה shchita in in these rings because they're not
considered to be part of the of the trachea itself because they
don't go all the way around. It says: Look the ברייתא Baraita
says רבי יוסף ברבי יהודה Rabbi Yosef be-Rabbi Yehuda says it is
part of the trachea you can do the שחיטה shchita there. תוספות
Tosafot reads it as saying whether doing a majority of these rings
is enough and it says: Since רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda רבי יוסף
ברבי יהודה Rabbi Yosef be-Rabbi Yehuda says you can do it there
presumably means you can do it there like you can do it
anywhere and a majority is enough. Okay so that's the argument so
you see רבי יוסף ברבי יהודה Rabbi Yosef be-Rabbi Yehuda says you
can שוחט shecht in these other rings and a majority according to
תוספות Tosafot a majority maybe is enough. ומוגרמת פסולה Umugremet pesula but
it is true that if you do הגרמה hagrama it's invalid you
move into the wrong space. העיד רבי חנינא בן אנטיגנוס He'id Rabbi
Chanina ben Antignos and רבי חנינא בן אנטיגנוס Rabbi Chanina ben Antignos
testified על מוגרמת שהיא כשרה al mugremet shehi keshera
this is quite fascinating that הגרמה hagrama is כשרה. keshera. So does
he only have four פסולים psulim doesn't have the פסול psul of
הגרמה? hagrama? So we're actually going to see no he has the
פסול psul of הגרמה hagrama but he means הגרמה hagrama as defined
here because he actually thinks that the מקום השחיטה makom hashchita is
כשרה keshera you can go much higher so just this defining it
as just within this top ring he doesn't agree that going out
of the top. offering is a problem. He does have הגרמה Hagrama
in a higher location. Okay, but the language sounds more absolute. Okay,
so let's take a look. אמר רב יוסף, Amar Rav Yosef, so
now we have this question. We see רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה Rabbi
Yossi Berabbi Yehuda says that שחיטה shechita in those rings is okay.
אמר רב יוסף, Amar Rav Yosef, רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה תרתי קאמר.
Rabbi Yossi Berabbi Yehuda tartei ka-amar. You're right, רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה
Rabbi Yossi Berabbi Yehuda said both. He did say you could שחיטה
shecht in those other rings. רב ושמואל סברי כוותיה בחדא ופליגי עליה
בחדא. Rav u-Shmuel savri k'vatei be-chada u-pligi lei be-chada.
They agree with him in one area, that it's enough to do
the majority by the top ring. They don't agree in the other
area where he says that you can do it in any of
the lower rings, they would disagree. The גמרא Gemara says והלא לא
אמרי הכי, ve-ha lo amri hachi, והלא אמר קאמרי, ve-ha lo amar
ka-amri, excuse me, והלא אמר קאמרי, ve-ha lo amar ka-amri,
but one minute, רב Rav and שמואל Shmuel said that רבי יוסי
ברבי יהודה Rabbi Yossi Berabbi Yehuda himself did not say his position
by the other rings. How can you say that he did say
the position, they're just not ruling like him? הכי קאמר, hachi ka-amar,
this is what it means. הלכה כמותו בטבעת גדולה. halacha k'moto be-taba'at
gedola. It doesn't mean that he didn't say it, it means that
we don't rule like him. So what they're saying is we rule
like him in the big ring at the top, that the majority
is enough, ואין הלכה כמותו בשאר טבעות. ve-ein halacha k'moto bi-shear taba'ot.
But not in the other rings. What not in the other rings?
Again, according to רש"י Rashi means you can't do שחיטה shechita in
the other rings, which would make life crazy, that if you tried
to do שחיטה shechita you had to get right between the rings.
And according to תוספות Tosafot it means no, by the other rings
it's not enough to do the majority of the ring, you have
to do the majority of the trachea, not the majority of the
ring, which is a more reasonable position. What? Because the ring doesn't
go all the way around. So תוספות Tosafot's read is much more
reasonable. Okay, let's see where the גמרא Gemara goes with it. כי
סליק רבי זירא, Ki salik Rabbi Zeira, when רבי זירא Rabbi Zeira
went to ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, אכל... achal... what? Is there a
problem?
Oh, this... thank you.
Ay-ay-ay.
Today is one of those days. Okay. Anyway, when רבי זירא Rabbi
Zeira went to
ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, אכל מוגרמת דרב ושמואל. achal mugremet de-Rav u-Shmuel.
He ate an animal that under רב Rav and שמואל Shmuel's definition
would be הגרמה. Hagrama. So what would this mean? So according to
רש"י Rashi it would mean that the שחיטה shechita was done in
the ring itself, or according to תוספות Tosafot it would mean that
the שחיטה shechita was done in the ring but only the majority
of the ring, not the majority of the trachea. But this case
that רב Rav and שמואל Shmuel said was no good, רבי זירא
Rabbi Zeira was not bothered with it and when he went to
ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, maybe when he was, and we'll see if
this is in the story, when he was in בבל Bavel he
was respectful to רב Rav and שמואל Shmuel's position, but he went
to ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael they didn't hold
of this problem, so he went ahead in ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael
he ate what they would have said was invalid.
That's a source for follow the local מנהג? minhag?
Well, you're... very good, we're going to get to that in a
minute. So אמרי ליה, amri lei, they said to him from ארץ
ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, לאו מאתריה דרב ושמואל את, lav me-atrei de-Rav u-Shmuel
at, don't you hail from the place of רב Rav and שמואל?
Shmuel? So what are you doing eating this type of animal? Eating
this type of שחיטה? shechita? אמר להו, amar lehu, he said to
them, מן אמרה? man amrah? Who said that רב Rav and שמואל
Shmuel said this position? יוסף בר חייא? Yosef bar Chiya? יוסף בר
חייא Yosef bar Chiya reported this in the name of רב Rav
and שמואל Shmuel because he was mentioned before as framing this position
of רב Rav and שמואל. Shmuel. הא, Ha, he said, יוסף בר
חייא מכולי עלמא גמירא, Yosef bar Chiya mi-chulei alma gemira, he just
heard it around on the street. He didn't really hear it directly
from רב Rav and שמואל. Shmuel. I don't believe רב Rav and
שמואל Shmuel really said this.
Does that mean he shouldn't have eaten it in בבל Bavel then?
Yeah. Okay, so it was nice. So presumably, let's see where the
story goes. שמע רב יוסף, Shama Rav Yosef, so רב יוסף Rav
Yosef heard that his testimony was being sort of questioned, איקפד, ikpad,
and he took it very personally. He was offended. אמר, Amar, he
said, אנא מכולי עלמא גמינא? Ana mi-chulei alma gamina? What, you think
that I just hear
from people on the street?
That's where I get my traditions from? אנא מרב יהודה גמירנא. Ana
mi-Rav Yehuda gamirna. I got this straight from רב יהודה, Rav Yehuda,
who was a student of רב Rav and שמואל, Shmuel, and not
only that, ודאפילו ספיקי דגברי גריס, ve-dafilu sefikei de-gavrei garis, and רב
יהודה Rav Yehuda was so precise in his traditions that even when
he had a doubt who he heard it from, he told us
what the doubt was. He was so exact in exactly what the
tradition was. How you know it?
דאמר מר, de-amar mar, exactly and honest, דאמר רב יהודה אמר רב,
de-amar Rav Yehuda Amar Rav, דאמר רב יהודה אמר רבי ירמיה בר
אבא, de-amar Rav Yehuda Amar Rabbi Yirmiya bar Abba, and then ספק
משמיה דרב ספק משמיה דשמואל, safek mishmei de-Rav safek mishmei de-Shmuel,
possibly in the name of
רב, Rav, possibly in the name of שמואל. Shmuel. So that's the
reason we're quoting this statement. When רב יהודה Rav Yehuda said something
over, if he had any doubt who said it, he would record
the doubt of who said it. Now what was the statement? This
is all parenthetical. שלשה מתירין את הבכור במקום שאין מומחה. Shlosha matirin
et ha-bechor be-makom she-ein mumche. When you want to allow to eat
a בכור bechor with a blemish, you have to show it to
a חכם chacham who can rule on the blemish. Even if it
is an obvious evident blemish that any idiot could see, it needs
a ruling by a חכם. chacham. But this statement was if you
don't have a חכם chacham available, you can take a בית דין
Beit Din of three people to rule on it even without a
חכם. chacham. Okay, so anyway, so now we have the issue that
רבי זירא Rabbi Zeira was saying I don't believe רב Rav and
שמואל Shmuel really said it, but they said back to him and
he doubt the report, but the response came back how dare you
doubt that report, of course רב Rav and שמואל Shmuel said it.
Any נפקא מינה nafka mina for second day יום טוב Yom Tov
then?
Well, okay, let's see where the גמרא Gemara ends with it. Yes.
I was just going to say, is by expert that means someone
was special סמיכה smicha for that?
Oh, yeah, there is a סמיכה smicha called יתיר בכורות. Yatir Bechorot.
It's not clear whether that's what it means in this context, because
we're also talking about a very evident blemish. Okay, so let's take
a look now. Now we get to the very interesting issue that
was raised about following the... Now we get to the very interesting
issue that was raised about following you know the different practices. So
the גמרא Gemara says ורבי זירא לית ליה נותנים עליו חומרי המקום
שיצא משם וחומרי המקום שהלך לשם? veRabbi Zeira leit lei notnim alav
chumrei hamakom sheyatza misham v'chumrei hamakom shehalach l'sham? But one minute doesn't
רבי זירא Rabbi Zeira say that you go by the stringencies of
the place you departed and the stringencies of where you're heading? So
if when he left בבל, Bavel, so if he left בבל Bavel
and this was the practice in בבל, Bavel, he should be continuing
this practice. So אמר אביי, amar Abaye, so אביי Abaye says, הני
מילי מבבל לבבל ומארץ ישראל לארץ ישראל. hani mili miBavel leBavel umiEretz
Yisrael leEretz Yisrael. That's if you're going from בבל Bavel to בבל
Bavel or from ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael to ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael.
You're going from like within one country to different places.
אי נמי ואפילו מארץ ישראל לבבל, i nami v'afilu miEretz Yisrael leBavel,
if you're going from ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael to בבל. Bavel. אבל
מבבל לארץ ישראל, aval miBavel leEretz Yisrael,
if you're going from בבל Bavel to Israel, then כיון דאנן כייפינן
להו. keivan d'anan kaifinan lehu. Very interesting statement to be coming from
the בבלי. Bavli. Since we are you know sort of subservient, thank
you, subject or subservient to them. כיון דאנן כייפינן להו עבדינן כוותייהו.
keivan d'anan kaifinan lehu avdinan kevataiyu.
We do like they do. Not when we're in בבל, Bavel, but
when we're in ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, we totally adopt the practices
of ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael because they are the ultimate authority vis-a-vis
בבל. Bavel. And we do not retain our Babylonian מנהגים minhagim when
we are in ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. Now this is a quite
fascinating גמרא Gemara from a—well yeah, but that's a different discussion. Anyway,
from a couple
of—well let's just finish it up and then I'll and then I'll
reflect on it. Okay. כיון דאנן כייפינן להו עבדינן כוותייהו. keivan d'anan
kaifinan lehu avdinan kevataiyu. We do like them. רב אשי אמר, Rav
Ashi amar, רב אשי Rav Ashi says, אפילו תימא מבבל לארץ ישראל,
afilu teima miBavel leEretz Yisrael, even if you would keep your practices
when you go from בבל Bavel to ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, הני
מילי היכא דדעתו לחזור. hani mili heicha d'da'ato lachazor. That's only if
you're planning on going back to בבל, Bavel, so you retain your
בבל Bavel practices. רבי זירא אין דעתו לחזור. Rabbi Zeira ein da'ato
lachazor. רבי זירא Rabbi Zeira made עליה aliyah and he stayed there.
He was not planning on returning so he was free to totally
keep the practices of ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael הוי. havei. Okay. Now
I want to reflect on this for a moment for two reasons—for
a few reasons. Number one, what does it mean that this is
putting this into the discussion of keeping your practices from בבל? Bavel?
If the reality is, meaning how did we leave off on the
discussion of whether רב ושמואל Rav v'Shmuel really said it or not?
Right? If רב ושמואל Rav v'Shmuel really said it and he really
was following the פסק psak of רב ושמואל Rav v'Shmuel when he
was in בבל, Bavel, it's not a question of your custom, it's
a question about how you've been פוסק'ן. paskening. Right? So do the
questions about how you פוסק, pasken, if I was in there and
I was following a פסק, psak, then the—then the question about keeping
the same פסק psak has to do with מנהג המקום? minhag hamakom?
Are those similar questions? Now in our common parlance we often conflate
the two ideas. We often say you know what's the מנהג, minhag,
but מנהג minhag can mean what's the custom—like something that's acknowledged to
be just a custom—or it could mean what is the practice and
it really means like whose you know whose ruling do you follow,
what's your practice? Not what's your custom, what's your practice. So normally
this issue of מנהג המקום שהלך ושיצא minhag hamakom shehalach v'sheyatza are
about custom, not about practice. So that's what תוספות Tosafot says. תוספות
Tosafot says the reason the גמרא Gemara shifted gears was that since
רבי זירא, Rabbi Zeira, although whoever it was, רב יוסף Rav Yosef
was taking umbrage, but since רבי זירא Rabbi Zeira was at least
making the claim that רב ושמואל Rav v'Shmuel did not really say
it, so what רבי זירא Rabbi Zeira was implicitly saying is I
never followed a פסק psak of רב ושמואל, Rav v'Shmuel, I questioned
whether רב ושמואל Rav v'Shmuel actually said it. I might have followed
the practice, the custom of doing that, but it was never in
the sense of following the פסק. psak. And then the גמרא Gemara
shifts gears and say oh, but even if it was just your
custom when you were in בבל, Bavel, shouldn't you be maintaining it
here? Okay but I mentioned that because it's possible to read the
גמרא Gemara otherwise. It's possible to read that רב יוסף Rav Yosef
took umbrage and the גמרא'ס Gemara's leaving by saying it really was
the פסק psak of רב ושמואל Rav v'Shmuel and then maybe saying
but maybe you're entitled to change your פסק psak when you move
to a place that has a different פסק. psak. And that raises
very interesting questions about how much does פסק, psak, not custom, but
פסק psak follow place? Okay but תוספות Tosafot insists on reading the
גמרא Gemara here about custom, not about פסק. psak. The other question
has to do with the relationship of ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael to
בבל. Bavel. You know there are other גמרות Gemaras that say the
opposite, that say that בבל Bavel had more authority than ארץ ישראל,
Eretz Yisrael, at least that they had more authority going back to
our earlier discussion to to impose their rulings. That when they ruled
on a case they actually had like a police force to back
them up more because they were given more authority by the Babylonian
Sassanian government than the Jews in ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael were. So
they actually you know their rulings had more backing. So תוספות Tosafot
says while that might be true that they might have had more
political authority and also authority to back up their rulings, but ultimately
the ultimate religious authority remained in ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael when it
came to the critical question of קידוש החודש. Kiddush Hachodesh. קידוש החודש
Kiddush Hachodesh was done by ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. רש"י Rashi also
mentions the issue of סמיכה smicha and who can do קנסות knasot
issues. Those remained in Israel which meant that ultimately even though there
was greater political authority whatever in בבל, Bavel, the ultimate religious authority
was Israel. The reason I also mention this is because the major
shift that occurred in the period of the גאונים, Geonim, which probably
ultimately made canonized the Babylonian תלמוד Talmud and is why we follow
the בבלי Bavli and not the ירושלמי, Yerushalmi, was when there was
a major split between when to make ראש השנה. Rosh Hashanah. There
was a major debate about the calendar and between בבל Bavel and
ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael and ultimately ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael insisted hey.
The גאונים Geonim of ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, you know, we're the
ultimate authority. And the גאונים Geonim of בבל Bavel said that's only
all other things being equal, but we have obviously much greater
in terms of חכמה, Chochma, so we outweigh you. And in the
end, you know, they were able to win not only because of
their argument, but because the whole center of gravity of the Jewish
community had shifted to בבל. Bavel. So in the end, the Babylonian
גאונים Geonim's ruling about what was ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh won out,
and that really was the מכה בפטיש, makeh b'patish, you know, of
ultimately acknowledging the authority of בבל Bavel over ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael.
That happened in the Geonic period. That has a lot to do
with why the בבלי Bavli is authoritative. Yes.
And why we're doing דף יומי Daf Yomi בבלי. Bavli.
Why by the בבלי Bavli and not by the ירושלמי? Yerushalmi? Exactly.
So let's just read one more line to wrap this up, and
let's take a look. So the גמרא Gemara says, so אמר ליה
אביי לרב יוסף, amlei Abaye l'Rav Yosef, so אביי Abaye said to
רב יוסף, Rav Yosef, והא רבנן דאתו ממחוזא אמרי אמר רב זירא
משמיה דרב נחמן מוגרמת כשירה. v'ha rabnan de-asv mi-Mechuza amri, amar Rav
Zeira mishmei de-Rav Nachman, mugremes keshera. But the Rabbis that came from
מחוזא Mechuza say in the name of רב זירא Rav Zeira in
the name of רב נחמן Rav Nachman that מוגרמת mugremes is כשרה,
kosher, which means that even in בבל, Bavel, in מחוזא, Mechuza, they
believed that it was כשרה. kosher. So you're saying רב Rav and
שמואל Shmuel in בבל Bavel said it was not acceptable, but now
we have a report that in מחוזא Mechuza they believed it was
acceptable, which is also in בבל. Bavel. So אמר ליה, amlei, he
said back to him, נהרא נהרא ופשטיה. nahara nahara u-pashtei. Very famous
phrase, which is a response, which is an important phrase in terms
of halachic pluralism, which means every river and its tributary. And the
way רש"י Rashi explains this in one place is he says you
could have the same river, in one place the waters are cold,
in the other place the waters are hot, in one place the
waters are salty, the same river branches off and each branch runs
its course. Which means yes we all follow one הלכה, halacha, but
every community has different practices, so even within בבל, Bavel, there are
some communities that rule that this is a problem and some communities
that rule that it is not a problem. Okay, so we will
end here. A very fascinating discussion about, you know, religious pluralism and
מנהג minhag and so on, within the context of the specific question
about this question of מוגרמת, mugremes, about either again if you go
too high or the issue about can you cut in the middle
rings within the trachea.